接下来这段就是我要在此视频要去制作的
video
[音频]
Hello, 我是 InspirAspir
在我们开始前
我想介绍一下
我的第一张EP "Dreamland"
在十一月三日发行
我相信在这个视频一周后
就会发布
如果你喜欢并支持我的工作
可以去听一听
这个视频会教你如何在 Ableton Live 10 中
制作你的第一首歌
我曾在 Live 9 做过类似的事
但未免有些过时
所以我想花些时间
带着一些新发现
来重新制作这个视频
来教你如何从零开始制作一首歌
ground rules for myself I will only be
并遵守
using default Ableton plugins just the
只使用 Live 自带插件
stock instruments audio effects that
和自带乐器和效果
没有三方插件
我将尽量使用 Live 10 中
相较于 Live 9
更新的乐器与效果
这样我就可以
让这个视频稍加不同
并更加现代
废话不多说
我们开始制作我们的第一首歌
你可以看到一个新的 Live 会话
在我的面前
这是创建一个新的 Live 会话是
默认的界面布局
我按下我的 Tab 键
来调整我的排列视图
现在你可以看到总共两条 MIDI 轨道
和两条音频轨道
MIDI 轨道是我们
要编写乐器需要演奏的音符的地方
音频轨道将
会被用于加载采样
首先我想设置这首歌的 BPM
现在只是一个粗略的估计
并可以随时根据自己喜好
来修改它
feeling maybe something around 80 bpm
现在我想让 BPM 在 80 左右
the lower the number the slower the song
BPM 越低， 曲速越慢
the higher the number the faster next I
BPM 越高， 曲速越快
want to start by making some chords this
我想从写和弦开始
is just a personal preference I like to
这是一个个人偏好
start with the chords and build from
我喜欢先写和弦
there to make some chords I first need
然后从那些和弦构建整首歌曲
to make a MIDI clip to do this I'm going
现在我要创建一个 MIDI 片段
to left click and drag for however long
我需要左键和拖拽
I want within a MIDI track in this case
我想要的 MIDI 轨道的长度
this is 17 bars long to make the MIDI
这样, 就有了 17 格
clip I'm gonna right click on my
现在右键我选中的
highlighted area and select insert MIDI
区域然后选 "Insert MIDI(插入 MIDI 片段)"
clip you
你
see this piano roll pop up if you don't
会看到这个钢琴卷弹出， 如果没有
be sure to double-click your MIDI clip
双击你的 MIDI 片段
from here I can click right about here
从这里我可以右键
my cursor will make this symbol which
我的光标会变成这样
allows me to click and drag upwards to
然后就可以点击然后向上拖动
expand the piano roll I can press the B
钢琴卷就会变大,
button on my keyboard to switch to the
draw mode you'll see this pencil pop up
and I can draw in some notes but if I
hit play the spacebar nothing happens
that's because I don't have any
instrument assigned so what I need to do
is go over into my Ableton library and
pick an instrument to do this I'm gonna
go under instruments and select my
instrument under these drop-down menus a
new instrument - Ableton Live 10
specifically is the wave table so let's
pretend I want to use the wave table
instrument to do that I'm going to
left-click and drag and drop onto my
MIDI track I'm gonna go back into my
piano roll again by double clicking and
now if I hit play quick tip if you want
to hear the sounds of your notes as you
click on them say for example you can do
so by clicking this button right here by
default it's grayed out click it it
turns blue now every time you draw on a
note you can hear that sound just
something to consider great so at this
point I can now start to make my chords
writing chords I feel like is out of
scope for this video that's more or less
a topic for another day but for now I'm
just gonna whip up some quick notes just
to get the point across okay so I've
gone ahead and created a chord
progression that I'm happy with for the
sake of this video a few things that I
did was that I just made some chords
they hit every bar so for at the end I
have them hitting every half bar and I
also changed my BPM what I'm trying to
get across here is that nothing's
necessarily locked in stone stay in my
BPM I can change that any time if I'm
not necessarily feeling it also get
creative with your chords you don't
necessarily have to have them hit every
bar you can change up a pattern maybe
have them hit every quarter
maybe you can have them hit in fifths
in fact yeah that's something I kind of
like so I'm gonna keep that so yeah I
made it so that these are fits so now
five chords hit in every bar and then at
the end here I actually changed that
pattern and I did a quarter followed by
needs the takeaway here I think is that
while music theory is important and good
to know also the rhythm is very
important too just because you have
something that sounds nice doesn't mean
it's catchy and potentially vice versa
so this is a chord progression I'm happy
with and for the most part I just want
this to loop one thing you can do is
you'll notice there's a bar up here I
can click and drag I'm going to move
this to the left and I'm gonna drag this
right end over to the end and actually
for now I'm just gonna go ahead and
delete this end bit this tail it's not
really needed so one thing I can do is I
can right click this bar and select a
loop so now I can press play and you'll
notice that it loops through this MIDI
clip now again here's another thing
that's kind of out of scope of this
video is just straight up sound design
that's kind of a beast in itself so for
the sake of again moving this video
along what I'm gonna do is just use a
preset that I like you can find presets
by going under instruments and then
under any of these subcategories so for
example maybe I like the wave table
it's new to Ableton Live 10 at which
point I can look for some sounds that I
like okay I found a preset that I like
under mallets Fizz bells sounds pretty
good to me now let's give our tracks
some bass something to go underneath
these chords to do this I'm gonna go
ahead and copy this MIDI clip and paste
it onto a different MIDI track and now
that we have two layers of our song I'm
gonna go ahead and rename these tracks
just to kind of organize our project a
little bit so over here this Fizz bells
track I just want to rename that I'm
gonna right-click and select rename I'm
gonna name this flux and then this
number to track the MIDI I'm gonna
rename that to bass and I like to color
these accordingly just again for the
sake of organization right click and I
can select a color and for now I'm
actually just gonna go ahead and delete
these two audio tracks just left click
on them and press the delete button okay
so now on to making our bass I don't
want any
hordes for my base I just want one
single note to play and the note that I
want to play is actually gonna be the
roots of my chords so I'm gonna go into
my base layers MIDI clip and just delete
all of the notes in each chord except
for the bottom I just want the last note
on the stack this is the root and
playing this alongside of the chords
should make a sound that I am pretty
happy with now I need to assign a bass
instrument to my MIDI track I think
maybe this one will be good let's try
this out
so one thing happened there that I'm not
particularly happy with one thing you
should always keep your eye on is the
volume level of your master track the
master track is the overall sound so
what you hear when you press play all of
the layers combined if you look down
here there's a layer called master if I
hit play right now there's kind of an
issue this went into the red this is
called clipping so basically he went
over the desired threshold and we don't
want that some ways to get around
clipping are to adjust the volumes of
your layers or to EQ them accordingly
which we'll get into in just a minute
but the point is I think this base layer
is just a little bit too loud so I could
either lower the volume of this base
layer or I could look for a different
instrument which I think I'm just gonna
do anyways okay so I found a base that I
like but this one actually is more or
less just a sub base this is under
operator base base sine like now this is
defined as a sub base because it only
takes up such low frequencies and I
actually kind of like that so I think
I'm gonna keep it now if you'll notice
if I hit play again I'm clipping a
little bit and actually it looks like my
plucks are pretty loud to you so I kind
of want to lower the volume of each of
these tracks and then I'll EQ them so
they fit in later but in order to lower
the volume of your tracks just go over
here where you see this zero click and
drag and you can lower it I'm gonna keep
this to about negative 2 decibels
essentially just a little bit quieter
I'm also gonna do the same with my bass
maybe lower just a little bit
I am still clipping but that's okay not
to be worried I'll be sure to clean up
the mix a little bit to make sure that's
fine
okay so this layer of base covers a lot
of the low end frequencies but now I
also want to cover some of the more
mid-range it's nice to have the rumble
of the sub base but I also want another
layer on top of it so to do that I'm
gonna rename this layer to sub base I'm
gonna copy it paste it rename the second
layer to maybe a mid base for this one I
want to find another instrument
something that maybe sounds a little bit
grittier kind of hefty okay this one
sounds kind of good at least for what
I'm trying to do for my own
organization's sake and also for some
other reasons I'll get into it a little
bit I want to group these two together
to do that I'm gonna click right here
hold the shift key and then select my
other MIDI track at which point I can
right click and select group tracks this
creates a group so the two tracks are
now bundled together
I can now rename this to bass now what I
want to do is EQ my layers a little bit
EQ essentially lets me cut off certain
ranges of frequencies that the sound
takes out and if you do it right it can
make your layers fit together like
puzzle pieces to find e queuing we can
go under audio effects and go to EQ I'm
gonna use an EQ 8 for the sake of this
video you can left-click and drag your
audio effects and drop it onto your MIDI
track so this is all my layer of sub
bass and for now I only want to listen
to this track to do that I'm gonna solo
this track by left-clicking right here
at this s button now if I hit play I
only hear this track if you look down
here you'll notice that this is the
audio waveform of this track and for the
most part I really only want frequencies
below I don't know something like a
hundred maybe 150 for this sub bass I'm
gonna click one of these drop-down
buttons and select this guy right here
this creates a low-pass filter where I
can set the frequency cutoff range I can
do that by left clicking and dragging
this little circle or by moving this
frequency knob what this says is
anything above 188 Hertz will not be
played it'll just be cut out of the mix
and so I'm gonna do what I said and more
or less just go about 100 maybe 120
you can hear the difference if I toggle
this low pass filter on or off
[音频]
you should hear some frequencies being
cut out there when this low-pass filter
is active I'm actually gonna change some
of these notes a little bit by the way
so I raised these notes over here by an
octave because it didn't really sound
good with the sub bass is too low now I
want to do the same thing with my
mid-range bass so I'm gonna solo this
track and add an EQ filter onto it now
I'm going to create a high-pass filter
so the opposite of a low-pass filter
cuts off anything below it I'm gonna set
that at about where my sub bass cuts off
so in this case maybe a hundred and
eleven issue I also want to create
another low-pass filter this time I'm
looking for one maybe around 400 this is
all really subjective it kind of depends
on your specific mix
I'm gonna go ahead and lower the notes
by an octave again do you make our bass
really stand out in this mix I'm
actually gonna put another EQ on our
bass group as a whole and then put a
low-pass filter at about 400 so just
really make sure that it's cutoff right
there and then I'm going to put an EQ on
our layer of plucks put in a high-pass
filter at that same exact cutoff so it's
more or less saying anything below 400
belongs to our basis anything above
belongs to our plucks
[音频]
okay so I'm pretty happy with that now
let's throw in some drums into the mix
to do this I want to make another MIDI
track I can right click in this empty
space and select insert MIDI track next
I'm going to go under drums drum rack
and drag that on to that MIDI track I
need to make a MIDI clip and then now if
I left click on this MIDI track you can
see this grid of squares this is where I
can drag in drum kick samples to be
played let's look under Ableton's
default drums to see what there is go
under drum hits let's go for some kicks
and just find a sample that I like I
kind of like this sample but I don't
really like the end of it but that can
be fixed so I'm gonna drag this into our
drum rack and I'm gonna move these start
and end Flags just to the parts that I
want maybe have it fade out a little bit
that sounds nice so now I can go into my
piano roll and you'll notice that my
sample is right here so I can draw in a
kick pattern so this is what I drew up
[音频]
some things you can do here to spice up
your drums are to add in some audio
effects onto your kick layer so maybe an
EQ if you go to EQ a drums able to
provide some good default kick each
cueing another thing we can do is
sidechaining this makes the volume of
other tracks dip every time this kick
plays you can do that by going to audio
effects compressor and drag that on to
let's say our overall base layer now
you'll see there's a compressor if I
select this arrow sidechain and then go
to drum rack let's actually rename that
to kicks now you'll see that it is side
change to the kicks I can click this
button right here and move this knob to
somewhere around here now if I hit play
our base is being side chained and we
can see that by clicking right here the
orange bar represents the volume so
every time this kick plays adjusting
this circle right here is a way of
adjusting how much you want it to
actually sidechain let's say that's a
good level of ducking what I can do is
copy this compressor and paste it onto
our pluck layer it really makes our
kicks shine it kind of pops through the
mix next let's add in some snares to
complement the kicks let's right click
insert MIDI track add in a drum rack and
then find some snares under drums drum
hits and let's go to snares now I
actually found two samples that I like
so let's drag them both into this drum
rack and then make a MIDI clip and let's
draw them both in whenever I want to
snare to play a point is what I'm trying
to say here is you can actually stack
the samples you can play them at any
point maybe even on top of each other
let's rename this two snares and I'm
actually gonna group my kicks and snares
together and call this percussion just
for the sake of organization now the
snares are kind of bland there's some
things you can do to spice them up
including maybe adding in some of the
cueing
which already sounds a little bit better
maybe we can add in things like glue
compressor maybe to make it a little bit
less harsh knowing your audio effects
and what they do is another element by
itself more or less for the sake of time
let's pretend this is good enough I also
want the other layers of my song to be
sidechain - my snares let's do the same
thing we did for the kicks but this time
a sidechain to our snares layer in fact
let's just copy this compressor and
paste it right next to it it's time
switching the side chaining audio from
kicks to the snares let's maybe have it
duck a little bit more it seems good to
me let's copy this paste it on to our
plucks at this point you can also add in
things maybe like some high hats or some
cymbals let's make another MIDI track
with a drum rack on top of it let's find
some high hats I found some high hats I
like at which point I can draw in a
pattern of high hats that I want ok
let's say that's a pattern that I like
let's also add in some cymbals I just
made a very simple pattern like this
[音频]
seems good to me let's also EQ this one
like we did for the other layers of the
percussion
and maybe adjust the volumes of each
element so maybe the high hats are a
little bit too loud
maybe these are also a little bit too
loud maybe let's also add in some reverb
okay so I'm pretty happy with that
maybe let's also add in another layer of
chords to complement our plucks I'm just
gonna copy and paste what I already have
for the plucks onto a different MIDI
track let's try and find a different
instrument that we might like for that I
found a pad layer that I like under
operator pad and glaciar voices I'm
gonna rename this to wide pad let's
group these two together I'm actually
gonna get rid of the sidechain on each
individual layer and just put it on the
overall group let's add in another pad
just for the sake of making the mix just
a little bit wider
I found this pad that's kind of
interesting again under operator pad
this time it's called still sky maybe I
want to lower the volume of this just a
little bit but as you can more or less
put together at this point I'm just kind
of adding elements on top of each other
just stacking layers but maybe let's
also add in a different layer maybe I
want to add in melody so let's add in a
layer of leads I'm picturing my leads to
be something xylophone II so I found
this brushed bail hit spell I guess
under operator mallets let's drag that
on and now let's get to writing on
melody okay so I whipped up melody real
quick here and I'm gonna do the same
thing for what I did with these pad just
more or less stack a lot of layers that
I'm happy with that I kind of want to
work together in
ok so I have a few that I'm happy with i
stacked guitar
I guess sitar guitar over here and the
FM one short lead and this is what it
sounds like
[音频]
melodies are another thing I'm chalking
up as more or less something I can't
cover in this video they're kind of a
thing of their own but the one tip I
will give is to stay in key and also
again as I mentioned before with the
chords music theory is important but
also so is rhythm you have to kind of
balance the two I'm gonna group these
together as I did before with everything
else and I'm gonna get to balancing each
of these I like how they sound together
but maybe not at their current volumes
I'm gonna throw some audio effects on
our overall group maybe an EQ again
maybe some compressors for the sink of
side-chaining but I'm actually gonna
lessen up on these ones just because
they're the leads and I want them to
kind of lay overtop the whole mix but I
still do want a little bit of
sidechaining in there maybe I can add in
some reverb maybe some delay of sorts
maybe a glue compressor at the end of it
all to kind of tie everything together
[音频]
and at this point I'm noticing certain
elements or maybe getting drowned out
for example our symbols so it's at this
point where you'd kind of go back and
tinker with everything on just the
volumes again nothing is ever really set
in stone as soon as you make it you're
allowed to go back and adjust things ok
so I just went back and I added another
layer of plucks I adjusted some volumes
just a little bit of tweaks here and
there so we have a nice loop here and
that's fine and dandy but to turn it
into an actual song we need to extend it
maybe actually it has to be a full
length song so 3 minutes or so point is
that can't really just be 20 seconds so
I'm gonna move this loop right here I'm
just gonna I'm just gonna left click and
drag and I'm gonna copy this and paste
it over here at which point maybe I want
to delete over this as well so now let's
make a transition maybe a quick quick
intro that kind of builds up and plays
into this little loop that we made maybe
I want to copy over the pads for example
I'm just kind of paste them over here
maybe I want them to be able to fade in
one thing I can do unable to ten is
switch to automation mode by pressing a
at which point you'll see a lot of these
red lines appear let's automate the
volume of our overall chords group track
I can do that by left clicking the
volume and you'll notice this red line
appeared I can automate this which means
I can change its value over time and so
maybe I want it to slowly fade in one
thing I can do is left-click and select
an anchor point right here and then
let's set another one at the beginning
now at this point I'm gonna left click
and drag it down and you'll notice that
I've lowered this to negative 10
decibels now if I were to hit play and
watch the volume over here it's
currently changing over time some things
you can do from here are add in some
more breakpoints to adjust the
automation you can hold the Alt key and
that selects this entire line I wish
want you can left-click and drag and
that creates a slope so let's have it
slowly fade in let's do the same thing
with our melody actually
want to copy and paste this over here
except I only want it to come in right
about here but I'm gonna do the same
thing with the volume I'm gonna automate
it another thing that can be potentially
is automate a low-pass filter so let's
add a low-pass filter right here maybe I
just want to cut off something really
high like sixteen thousand what I can do
is I can click this knob and automate
that as well so if I were to set a
breakpoint right here and then maybe
right here I can have it be lower I can
essentially have this EQ filter automate
over time let's get rid of some of these
layers and then finally let's wrap it up
by adding in a transition sound effect
let's right click over here and insert
audio track let's go over under drums
maybe find a ride this one sounds pretty
good to me something long let's drag it
on to our audio track let's double click
it and actually hit this button right
here this reverses the sample now if I
were to hit play
now it's sounding a little bit weird and
that's because it's warped one thing I
also want to do is unclick this button
right here it says warp now let's zoom
in and drag this right over here and so
now I have a very basic transition sound
effect but I feel like it's coming in
maybe a little too soon so let's drag
this over by left clicking the end over
here dragging it and let's hit the a
button to leave automation mode at which
point when I hover over this sound
effect you'll notice there's four
squares that show up on each corner
let's left-click this one and drag it in
this controls the volume of the sound
effect so essentially it's slowly coming
in it's fading in over time I can move
this little icon right here to change
the slope of the line finally let's
right click insert audio track let's add
in one more ride a simple sound effect
at the beginning of this loop so it kind
of rises up into this reverse cymbal but
then it also crashes as soon as this
loop starts this sounds good to me let's
make sure this isn't warped as well
[音频]
must maybe lower the volume of this real
quick and I think that should do it
that's you know the very basics of
making your first song what you do at
this point is more or less just take
what you just learned and kind of extend
that to make an entire full length track
you'd then also have to export your song
which you can which you can do by going
to file export audio and video and then
you'd also have to make sure that your
track is mastered that's another process
in of itself but there you have it
that's pretty much it that's the basics
of making your first song I hope you
enjoyed the video I hope you learned
something consider checking out my new
EP coming out November 3rd very excited
for them to come out and thanks for
watching
[音频]